-and not have to blindly rely on priests or illuminated kings.
Diderot collects over a hundred employees in the project-
-The so -called encyclopedists.
Here they are on a group board.
The French encyclopedia with 70,000 articles took 40 years to write.
There they tried to gather everything knowing.
It was a fantastic idea.
There, the 18th century man can learn everything from baking and surgery-
-To fencing and clock building ...
... in ordinary language, with pictures, to form people.
It becomes a bestseller, even though we talk about heavy volumes.
Encyclopedia is typical of the epoch known as enlighten-
-This, the lantern of reason should light up in the darkness of ignorance.
But what was the enlightenment?
What more than encyclopedia wrote and read?
The enlightenment occurs in Europe in the 17th century-
-And becomes the leading stream of ideas in the West throughout the 18th century.
Now great progress is taking place in science.
Isaac Newton gets an apple in the head and lists how the law of gravity works.
The two central countries are the UK and France-
-But also in Sweden the idea of ideas is visible.
We have Carl von Linné with his classifications.
Anders Celsius defines a temperature scale-
-When he a little humble baptizes for himself.
However, despite the gravity and a temperature based on the properties of the water-
-Is life no dance on roses for the 18th century man.
The 18th century Sweden is very unpleasant.
It stinks terribly.
Sweden was not unique.
The 18th century was disgusting for almost everyone.
We have nothing similar to modern welfare.
No, it's not fun for most people.
Here somewhere the thought-
-They if man can tame science-
-Why can't we tame and make the whole community better?
The great news with the enlightenment-
-while is a water divider of historical proportions-
-Is to affirm change.
Power lies with two authorities: the church and the state.
They decide everything and have patents on the explanatory models.
There are very few in the 18th century who do not believe in god-
-But many are starting to question the church as an institution.
Central is the revolutionary idea that all people can think for themselves-
-And that we are free and independent.
"Freedom" is probably the most beloved word of enlightenment.
You also attach great importance to reason.
The English philosopher John Locke says we are born as unwritten leaves.
The empty leaf is filled during life.
What is our reason are our overall experiences and knowledge-
-So what is now on our paper.
Society bubbles with optimism.
Through science and reason you can solve the world's problems.
The optimism is also visible in the literature.
By reading novels, people can understand themselves and develop.
It is in the UK that it takes off.
The fact that the novel begins to bloom in the UK is due to the book market.
There are readers, printers and publishers.
A book that many on the British Isles read takes place on an island-
-dock not an equally densely populated one.
Where in his loneliness lives a man who loves reason-
-and to fill sitting empty leaves with knowledge.
This is the book "Robinson Crusoe" by Englishman Daniel Defoe.
The adventure novel "Robinson Crusoe" comes out in 1719 and makes incredible success.
Defoe becomes world famous and the book becomes one of the world's most translated.
The action is well known.
Book poiler: "Robinson Crusoe".
Robinson Crusoe suffers shipwreck and drives alone in land-
-On a nearly uninhabited island.
He salvages some things from the wreck-
-and thanks to common sense and inventive wealth-
-He builds his own community on the island.
He lives alone until he gets social
-When a man he rescues from the cannibals.
He baptizes him a little slim until Friday after the day of the week-
-And Friday becomes his servant.
Finally, after 28 years, 2 months and 19 days-
-Red Robinson and can return home.
Robinson embodies the ideal of enlightenment.
He is sensible and practical.
He solves problems by observing and learning from his mistakes.
When he does in the way of enlightenment - acting with reason-
-He changes his poor life on the island to an idyllic existence.
He is incurable optimist.
He does not panic by loneliness-
-On struggles and believes in himself and his ability to solve problems.
Robinson Crusoe is a man of action.
He is driven by a Protestant Christian, moral thought-
-To work is the best.
It lifts man and makes us better.
When the book comes out, many believe that the story is true.
It is written in I-form and the word "I" is common.
It is a novel that will attract stretch reading.
It should be exciting and accessible to many.
One has pointed to the problematic, imperialist thought-
-Do the only culture and civilization that counts is the European-
-and in this case the English.
When Robinson Crusoe comes-
-The he saves Friday from his lost condition.
There have been protests against it, and writers have made other versions.
For example, Michel Tournier has written the book-
-"Friday or a life in freedom".
There he recounts Defoe's story from Friday's point of view.
The enlighteners had probably been proud of the criticism.
To question, after all, was a supporting part of what you did.
The language of "Robinson Crusoe" is in I-form.
In some parts it is written as a diary.
Robinson as a person was really arrogant.
He thinks he is the best and that he is better than others.
But I would also say that he is really smart-
-And really fights well, because he doesn't give up.
But the book requires patience.
In the beginning I got tired and wanted to stop reading.
Then it will be fun because you see everything in front of you.
It should spread the enlightenment to the masses.
Literature is used to convey messages.
Part of the enlightenment philosophers-
-As also what we today call fictional writers.
The middle -class activity reading is therefore not just about entertainment.
It gives the author a chance to raise the reader.
It is no coincidence that one suddenly gets the novel-
-which can discuss in fictional form.
Science, how we can think philosophically about different things life ...
How do you become a good person?
How do we live good lives?
Several philosophers become fictional writers to reach out with the ideas.
We have Jean-Jacques Rousseau which in 1762 publishes the book "émile".
On the surface it is about a young man without parents-
-But is really an instruction book in child rearing.
"Raised in rural simplicity, your children get a clearer voice."
"There, they do not acquire the stuttering of the city children."
During the enlightenment, fiction is used, with straight language-
-As a tool for learning, raising and making us better people.
There is a completely different style that is in contrast to the skill fixation.
It provokes, attracts to laughter and writes awful things-
-To arouse emotions and debate: the satire.
In the 18th century, satire is used to criticize society.
It is not only funny, but should improve.
Other enlightenment literature mediated knowledge-
-But the satire was used to criticize the maladminist-
-dolt behind jokes.
A index finger with clown peruk against the authorities.
A well -known example of satire is Jonathan Swift who wrote ...
He is best known for "Gulliver's travels"-
He pretends to be serious and leaves this "humble suggestion"-
-If raising Irish, poor families' children so that they become obese-
-and you can eat them.
It became a scream when people read.
If you do not understand that it is satire, "a humble proposal" is completely ill.
"A child becomes two dishes when invitation for friends"-
-"And when the family dines alone, Framfjärding becomes a decent dish"-
-"especially winter time with pepper or salt."
"Let hang three days before it is cooked."
Despite the absurd content, the text is factual and logical.
It is presented as a scientific solution to a difficult problem.
In addition to Swift's prompt to eat child-
-e one of the enlightenment's most famous works a satir-
-written by another central figure, Voltaire.
He was also one of the encyclopedists.
The most well-known Enlightenment Agency is Voltaire's short novel "Candide"-
-Or also has an eternal readership, because it's fun.
It is written with a twinkle in the eye and is a satire about how the kingdoms guide-
-If prevailing philosophies and on -understanding.
Voltaire inspired Swedish Anna Maria Lenngren-
-As used jokes and satire in their poems.
She is an exciting writer with a very broad production.
She was known for her irony, and there is the most famous-
-and debated the poem she wrote-
-"A few words to my dear daughter, if I had any".
"With reading not time away, our gender so little it needs."
"And should you read, make it short, that the sauce must not mill over."
Women should therefore preferably not read and educate themselves-
-And if they do, do it quickly to avoid chaos in the kitchen.
Or?
For a long time it was believed that it was serious, and that Lenngren was conservative.
Now we know that the poem is multifaceted.
It is skilfully rhetorically designed.
Among other things, Lenngren uses irony.
So the reverse message is-
-That women should of course have education.
The written satire could be mixed with something forbidden - pornography.
Researchers have shown that pornography could be used as a social criticism-
-and spreading malicious rumors about what the king and the queen did.
There were serious things that were sold freshly on the streets of Paris and spread in the country.
It was forbidden literature.
Much of the criticism is aimed at the monarchy, the king and the queen.
It is mainly in France - a central country - like that speed.
You are tired of poverty and injustice.
We have a community that almost bubbles over of restrained anger-
-Above how terribly unfair and bad it is.
Do you remember Diderot, he with encyclopedia?
In addition to conveying knowledge in thick books, he said this ...
Diderot says:
"Man is not free until the last king has been strangled"-
-"of the last priest's intestines."
Hard words!
And in the late 18th century it breaks loose in France.
The enlightenment ideas will become a reality and the dream community is really built.
There is revolution going on.
Here is the revolutionary spark.
One claims that there is no reason-
-To a small elite should control a majority of the population.
The people should control and legislate over their own destiny.
The French Revolution leads to the overthrow of the king-
-But then it goes quickly.
People literally lose their heads, almost everywhere.
All suspected counter -revolutionaries are at risk of getting ...
... during the guillotine that starts to walk on treadmills, publicly in Paris.
The revolution, which would make enlightenment ideas to reality-
-The leads to a bloody horror.
Building the perfect community with reason proves more difficult-
-Ever it was to rewrite.
Enlightenment and the 18th century end with revolution, war and death-
-But much of the ideas and literature still lives on today.
The enlightenment is an exciting time, and extremely important.
This is where modern democracy is launched, with freedom and equality.
The Swedish Academy was also founded under the Enlightenment-
-And the literature began to be seen as an institution.
Satire - using jokes with cape - is today a common grip.
The very idea of looking at society, see where improvements-
-And make his voice heard, it also lives on from the enlightenment.
The idea that man can change his world and reflect on it-
-Set up and criticize, thus change ...
The message that you can do this is the enlightenment's legacy to us.
Some love and others despise it.
It is probably related to the fact that so much light creates strong shadows.
Text: No Ollars www.btistudios.com